The Life Of Muhammadﷺ Madinan Period Volume 2,
By Imam Anwar Al_Awlaki,
اَعُوْذُ بِاللهِ مِنَّ الشِّيْطَانِ الرَّجِيْمِ۝بِسْمِ اللهِ الرَّحْمَانِ الرَّحِيْمَ۝
اَلْحَمْدُ لله ، وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِنَا محمد وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْرا
Dear brothers and sisters ألسلام عليكم ورحمة الله وبركاته.
Al-Imam Ahmad(ألاِمَامْ اَحْمَدْ) narrates with an authentic chain of narration,
عَنْ أَبِي سَعِيدٍ الْخُدْرِيِّ
قَالَ : لَمَّا أَعْطَى رَسُولُ اللَّهِ صَلَّى اللَّهُ عَلَيْهِ وَسَلَّمَ مَا أَعْطَى مِنْ ذلْكَ الْعَطَايَا فِي قُرَيْشٍ وَقَبَائِلِ الْعَرَبِ
وَلَمْ يَكُنْ فِي الْأَنْصَارِ مِنْهَا شَيْءٌ وَجَدَ هَذَا الْحَيُّ مِنَ الْأَنْصَارِ فِي أَنْفُسِهِمْ
حَتَّى كَثُرَتْ فِيهِمُ الْقَالَةُ حَتَّى قَالَ قَائِلُهُمْ : لَقِيَ رَسُولُ اللَّهِ صَلَّى اللَّهُ عَلَيْهِ وَسَلَّمَ قَوْمَهُ
فَدَخَلَ عَلَيْهِ سَعْدُ بْنُ عُبَادَةَ ،
فَقَالَ : يَا رَسُولَ اللَّهِ ، إِنَّ هَذَا الْحَيَّ قَدْ وَجَدُوا عَلَيْكَ فِي أَنْفُسِهِمْ
لِمَا صَنَعْتَ فِي هَذَا الْفَيْءِ الَّذِي أَصَبْتَ ، قَسَمْتَ فِي قَوْمِكَ ، وَأَعْطَيْتَ عَطَايَا عِظَامًا فِي قَبَائِلِ الْعَرَبِ
وَلَمْ يَكُن فِي هَذَا الْحَيِّ مِنَ الْأَنْصَارِ شَيْءٌ ،
قَالَ : فَأَيْنَ أَنْتَ مِنْ ذَلِكَ يَا سَعْدُ ؟
قَالَ : يَا رَسُولَ اللَّهِ ، مَا أَنَا إِلَّا امْرُؤٌ مِنْ قَوْمِي ،
قَالَ : فَاجْمَعْ لِي قَوْمَكَ فِي هَذِهِ الْحَظِيرَةِ
قَالَ : فَخَرَجَ سَعْدٌ ، فَجَمَعَ الْناسَ فِي تِلْكَ الْحَظِيرَةِ ،
قَالَ : فَجَاءَ رِجَالٌ مِنَ الْمُهَاجِرِينَ ، فَتَرَكَهُمْ ، فَدَخَلُوا وَجَاءَ آخَرُونَ ، فَرَدَّهُمْ
فَلَم يجْتَمَعُوا أَتَاهُ سَعْدٌ فَقَالَ : قَدِ اجْتَمَعَ لَكَ هَذَا الْحَيُّ مِنَ الْأَنْصَارِ
قَالَ : فَأَتَاهُمْ رَسُولُ اللَّهِ صَلَّى اللَّهُ عَلَيْهِ وَسَلَّمَ فَحَمِدَ اللَّهَ وَأَثْنَى عَلَيْهِ ، بِالَّذِي هُوَ لَهُ أَهْلٌ
ثُمَّ قَالَ : يَا مَعْشَرَ الْأَنْصَارِ مَا قَالَةٌ بَلَغَتْنِي عَنْكُمْ وَجِدَةٌ وَجَدْتُمُوهَا فِي أَنْفُسِكُمْ ،
أَلَمْ آتِكُمْ ضُلَّالًا فَهَدَاكُمُ اللَّهُ ؟
وَعَالَةً فَأَغْنَاكُمُ اللَّهُ ؟ وَأَعْدَاءً فَأَلَّفَ اللَّهُ بَيْنَ قُلُوبِكُمْ ؟ ،
قَالُوا : بَلِ اللَّهُ وَرَسُولُهُ أَمَنُّ وَأَفْضَلُ
قَالَ : أَلَا تُجِيبُونَنِي يَا مَعْشَرَ الْأَنْصَارِ
قَالُوا : وَبِمَاذَا نُجِيبُكَ يَا رَسُولَ اللَّهِ ، وَلِلَّهِ وَلِرَسُولِهِ الْمَنُّ وَالْفَضْلُ
قَالَ : أَمَا وَاللَّهِ لَوْ شِئْتُمْ لَقُلْتُمْ فَلَصَدَقْتُمْ وَصُدِّقْتُمْ ، أَتَيْتَنَا مُكَذَّبًا فَصَدَّقْنَاكَ ، وَمَخْذُولًا فَنَصَرْنَاكَ ، وَطَرِيدًا فَآوَيْنَاكَ ، وَعَائِلًا فَآغنَيْنَاكَ
أَوَجَدْتُمْ فِي أَنْفُسِكُمْ يَا مَعْشَرَ الْأَنْصَارِ فِي لُعَاعَةٍ مِنَ الدُّنْيَا ، تَأَلَّفْتُ بِهَا قَوْمًا لِيُسْلِمُوا ، وَوَكَلْتُكُمْ إِلَى إِسْلَامِكُمْ ؟
أَفَلَا تَرْضَوْنَ يَا مَعْشَرَ الْأَنْصَارِ أَنْ يَذْهَبَ النَّاسُ بِالشَّاةِ وَالْبَعِيرِ ، وَتَرْجِعُونَ بِرَسُولِ اللَّهِ صَلَّى اللَّهُ عَلَيْهِ وَسَلَّمَ  فِي رِحَالِكُمْ ؟
فَوَالَّذِي نَفْسُ مُحَمَّدٍ بِيَدِهِ لَوْلَا الْهِجْرَةُ لَكُنْتُ امْرَأً مِنَ الْأَنْصَارِ ، وَلَوْ سَلَكَ النَّاسُ شِعْبًا ، وَسَلَكَتِ الْأَنْصَارُ شِعْبًا لَسَلَكْتُ شِعْبَ الْأَنْصَارِ
اللَّهُمَّ ارْحَمِ الْأَنْصَارَ ، وَأَبْنَاءَ الْأَنْصَارِ ، وَأَبْنَاءَ أَبْنَاءِ الْأَنْصَارِ
قَالَ : فَبَكَى الْقَوْمُ ، حَتَّى أَخْضَلُوا لِحَاهُمْ ،
وَقَالُوا : رَضِينَا بِرَسُولِ اللَّهِ قِسْمًا وَحَظًّا ، ثُمَّ انْصَرَفَ رَسُولُ اللَّهِ صَلَّى اللَّهُ عَلَيْهِ وَسَلَّمَ وَتَفَرَّقُوا
This is a narration by Imam Ahmad(اِمَامْ اَحْمَدْ) and it's authentic
and there's also equivalent narrations with some changes in the wordings
by Al-Bukhari(ألبخاريْ) and Muslim(مسلم) and other books of Hadith(حديث)
and it is narrated by Abu Saeed Al-Khudari(أبوسعيد ألخدري). He said;
When Rasool Allah ﷺ gave, out the spoils of Hunain(حنين) to Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), and the Arab tribes.
You see, the spoils of war of Hunain(حنين) were huge,
because remember, Malik Bin Auf(مالك بن عوف) took everything with him, women, children, and livestock.
So, it was all there, as soon as they fled the Muslims took everything with them.
It was a huge amount of camels and goats and sheep.
Rasool Allah ﷺ just finished from Fateh Makkah(فتح مكه).
And he has a large army with him, that includes people, who came for the first time.
Some of these Arab tribes from outside Madina and the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
I mean, for the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) this was the first time
and for some of the other tribes their involvement in Ghazoo(غزؤ) was rare,
but because this was a major expedition Rasool Allah ﷺ mobilized all of the Muslims to join him.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ started giving out from the spoils of war to Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), and to the other Arab tribes.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ gave Safwaan Ibn Ummayyah(صفوان إبن أمية) from Quraish(قُرَيْشْ)
and he gave people like a Aqrah Bin Habis(ألأقره بن حابس), and Uyainah Bin Hassan(عيينه بن حصن)
these are leaders of some of the Bedouin tribes.
And he gave Al-Abbas Bin Mardaas(ألعباس بن مرداس), who was the head of the tribe of Bannu Sulaim(بنو سليم).
Rasool Allah ﷺ gave everyone, and he only left out one tribe, and that tribe, is Al-Ansaar(ألأنْصَار).
So, Subhaan Allah(سبحان الله) the ones who fled, were given, and the ones who fought went empty handed.
And the Ansaar(أنْصَار), were saddened by that,
I mean in the time of fighting Rasool Allah ﷺ calls us and then the time of giving, he gives someone else.
We were the ones, whom Rasool Allah ﷺ called
when Rasool Allah ﷺ was standing and everybody else was running away,
who did Rasool Allah ﷺ called for.?
He said;
يا للانصار ,
He told Al-Abbas(العباس), call the Ansaar(أنْصَار).
And then he told them: Call Al-Khazraj(ألخزرج).
So, these are the ones who came to fight, and were injured, and were killed.
And now, when it's time to split the Ghaneemah(غنيمه).
Rasool Allah ﷺ is giving everyone but them.
So, there was some talk going on, among the Ansaar رضي الله عنهم, and they were sad by this and
their leaders Saad Ibn Ubadah(سعد ابن عبادة), had to go to Rasool Allah ﷺ and bring up the issue.
So, he went to Rasool Allah ﷺ and said;
یا رسول اللہ إِنَّ هَذَا الْحَيَّ قَدْ وَجَدُوا عَلَيْكَ فِي أَنْفُسِهِمْ لِمَا صَنَعْتَ فِي هَذَا الْفَيْءِ الَّذِي أَصَبْتَ
قَسَمْتَ فِي قَوْمِكَ ، وَأَعْطَيْتَ عَطَايَا عِظَامًا فِي قَبَائِلِ الْعَرَبِ ، وَلَمْ يَكُن فِي هَذَا الْحَيِّ مِنَ الْأَنْصَارِ شَيْءٌ
O Messenger of Allah, these people, the Ansaar(انصار), are sad
because you have given your people
and you have given great portions, to the leaders of the Arab tribes.
For example Al-Aqraa(الاقراه) was given 100 camels and
Uyeynaa(عيينه) a 100 camels and then Al-Abbas Bin Mardaas(ألعباس بن مرداس) was given 50
but then it was raised to 100.
And these are يعني hundred camels يعني a camel is very expensive,
so 100 camels is a big portion that is it's such a great amount of wealth.
وَلَمْ يَكُن فِي هَذَا الْحَيِّ مِنَ الْأَنْصَارِ شَيْءٌ ،
And the Ansaar(أنْصَار) are empty handed.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ asked Saad Ibn Ubadah(سعد ابن عبادة), he told him
فَأَيْنَ أَنْتَ مِنْ ذَلِكَ؟
Where do you stand, O Saad(سعد)?
Saad Ibn Ubadah رضي الله عنه said;
يَا رَسُولَ اللَّهِ ، مَا أَنَا إِلَّا امْرُؤٌ مِنْ قَوْمِي
I am but I man from my people.
That's a very intelligent way of saying that, I have, same question to ask?
He is saying but I'm but one man from my people,
he came and presented to Rasool Allah ﷺ the opinion of his people
and when Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Where do you stand.?
He said: I am but a man from my people.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
قَالَ: فَاجْمَعْ لِي قَوْمَكَ فِي هَذِهِ الْحَظِيرَةِ ،
Bring all of your people together in this pavilion.
قَالَ : فَخَرَجَ سَعْدٌ ، فَجَمَعَ الْأَنْصَارَ فِي تِلْكَ الْحَظِيرَةِ ،
Saad Ibn Ubadah رضي الله عنه went and gathered the Ansaar(أنْصَار) in the appointed pavilion.
فَجَاءَ رِجَالٌ مِنَ الْمُهَاجِرِينَ ، فَتَرَكَهُمْ ، فَدَخَلُوا وَجَاءَ آخَرُونَ ، فَرَدَّهُمْ ،
and they were allowed to come in,
and while some others came and Rasool Allah ﷺ turned them back.
This is a special meeting for Al-Ansaar(ألأنْصَار),
but he did allow some of the Muhajireen(مهاجرين), who were his advisors and some important people to come in,
but the rest were prevented from entering.
This is a private meeting between Rasool Allah ﷺ, and the Ansaar(أنْصَار).
فَلَمَّا اجْتَمَعُوا أَتَاهُ سَعْدٌ فَقَالَ : قَدِ اجْتَمَعَ لَكَ هَذَا الْحَيُّ مِنَ الْأَنْصَارِ ،
When they were all there Rasool Allah ﷺ was told by Saad(سعد), the Ansaar(أنْصَار) have gathered.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ came, and the gathering was all ready, everybody was there before Rasool Allah ﷺ.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ came in and they were all in the tent or the pavilion.
فَحَمِدَ اللَّهَ وَأَثْنَى عَلَيْهِ ،
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ praised Allah, and thanked Him.
And that is how, we should start our major events, our talks,
we start them, by praising Allahعَزّوجَلّ, that is the Sunnah(سنة).
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ spoke to the Ansaar(أنْصَار), these words.
He said: Didn't I come to you and you were misguided and Allah guided you through me.?
I came to you, when you were poor and Allah enriched you through me.?
I came to you and you're enemies, and Allah brought you together.?
They responded and said: All favors belong to Allah and His Messenger
everything that Rasool Allah ﷺ said: We agree.
And all of these favors that you mentioned they belong to Allah and to you.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ told them. Well, won't you answer back.?
They said: What should we say,? When all favors belong to Allah, and His Messenger.!
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: In the name of Allah.
If you want, you may say, and you would be telling the truth if you do,
you came to us rejected, and we believed in you.!
You were betrayed and we supported you.
You were refugitive, and we provided you with the home.
You were poor, and we enriched you.
O, people of Al-Ansaar(ألأنْصَار), Are you upset,
because of a small material gain that I am using to bring, a people closer to Islam, while I have entrusted you to your Islam.!
Aren't you content O people of Al-Ansaar(ألأنْصَار), That people would go back with sheep and camels
while you would go back to your homes with Rasool Ullah.
In the name of whom Muhammad(محمد)'s soul is in His hands.
If it wasn't for Hijrah(هجرة), I would be a man from Al-Ansaar(الأنْصَار).
And if people take a road and the Ansaar(أنْصَار), take another road, I would follow the road of Al-Ansaar(الأنْصَار)
O Allah, forgive, Al-Ansaar(الأنْصَار),
The sons of Al-Ansaar(الأنْصَار). And the grandsons of Al-Ansaar(الأنْصَار).
Abu Saeed Al-Khudri(ابوسعيد الخدري) say; They cried, they started crying, until their beards were wet
and they said: We are pleased with Rasool Allah ﷺ as our share.
Al-Ansaar(الأنْصَار) are special, and Rasool Allah ﷺ told them that,
you are different than the rest of the people.
I'm giving the other people this money to bring them closer to Islam
but I trust your Emaan(ايمان) and I trust your faith and I know that
you are not in need of these worldly things to bring you closer to me and bring you closer to Allah,
you already have that in your hearts.
The Ansaar(انصار), when they first met with Rasool Allah ﷺ
what was the deal between them and Rasool Allah ﷺ?
We support you and we fight for you and what do we get in exchange of that?
Al-Jannah(الجنة).
Rasool Allah ﷺ did not promised them Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) from day one.
The Ansaar(أنْصَار), we're in it, for the right reasons.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ is reminding them with the blessings of Allah that came to Al-Ansaar(الأنصار),
when Rasool Allah ﷺ arrived in Madina.
They were misguided, they were Kuffar(كفار), and what is a greatest disaster than being a Kafir(كافر)
And they were guided through Muhammadﷺ, and what is the greater blessing than that
nothing,
nothing counts when you compare it to the blessing of Hidayah(هداية).
And that's why brothers and sisters
the most frequent Dua(دعا) that we make is Dua(دعا) we say in Fatiha(فاتحه),
اِهْدِنَا الصِّرَاطَ الْمُسْتَقِيمَ
Guide us to the straight path.
That is better for us than money, it's better than women, it's better than children.
It's better than having a house, it's better than everything.
The best thing that you could have, better than having being healthy.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ told them: And you were poor and Allah enriched you.
How did Allah enriched them?
I mean, in terms of the economy of Madina before it was based on agriculture
and agriculture in Madina was actually going down because of the constant state of war that they were in,
because of the Hijrah(هجرة) of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
So, what does Rasool Allah ﷺ means enriched you through me?
It means through the Ghanaem(غنائم) that are coming from Jihad(حهاد) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله).
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ said: And you were enemies
Al-Aos(الأوس) and Khazraj(خزرج) were at the throats of each other, and Allah has brought them together.
So, they agreed and they said: All favors belong to Allah and His Messenger.
We can't reject that and we can't complain!
But then Rasool Allah ﷺ told them;
On the other hand, you could also, tell me, that I was rejected by my people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
And it is, we who believe.
You can say that you were betrayed by your people and we are the ones, who supported you.
You can say that you were a refugitive and you had nowhere to go.
And there was a bounty on you.
And it is we, who provided you with the home and a base to spread the Da'wah(دعوة) from.
And you could also say that Rasool Allah ﷺ was poor and he had nothing and we are the ones, who hosted him.
But the Ansaar(أنْصَار) obviously would not say that, they would not complain,
they would not brag about, what they have done.
Because they consider everything to be a blessing from Allahعَزّوجَلّ
and everything good that they did, they considered it to be from Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ is telling them that, this is a small material gain.
لُعَاعَةٍ مِنَ الدُّنْيَا
And I'm giving it to these people not because I love them, not because I like them.
It is because I want to bring them closer to Islam.
أَتَألَّفْهُمْ
These are called;
مُؤلَّفُة قُلُوْبُهُمْ
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ told them something,
which only people who understand the greatness of Rasool Allah ﷺ
he told them that people are going back with sheep and camels,
while you are going back to your homes with Rasool Ullah.
I am going back with you, I'm not going to stay in Makkah, I'm going back with you.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ is telling them that if it wasn't for Hijrah(هجرة),
because Rasool Allah ﷺ is counted as a Muhajir(مهاجر)
which is a greater status then Ansaari(انصاري).
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ says; If it wasn't for Hijrah(هجرة).
I would count myself as a member of Al-Ansaar(ألأنْصَار)
and then Rasool Allah ﷺ is telling them, if all the people take a certain road,
while you take another road, I would follow yours, I would be with you.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ made this lovely Dua(دعا) for Al-Ansaar(الأنْصَار);
O Allah forgive the Ansaar(انصار), Forgive the sons of Al-Ansaar(ألأنصار),
And forgive the grandsons of Al-Ansaar(ألأنصار)!
And this, when the Ansaar رضي الله عنهم heard these words they cried, until their beards were wet.
And they said: We are pleased with Rasool Allah ﷺ.
There are different narrations as I mentioned in Bukhari(بخاريْ) and Muslim(مسلم)
in one of them there was a statement that caught my attention.
Hishaam(هشام) says;
قُلْتِ يَا اَبَا حَمْزَه وَاَنْتَ شَاهِدْ ذَالِكْ، قَالَ: اَنَس أغيب عنه
Hishaam(هشام), who's the Tabie(تابعي) narrating the Hadith(حديث) is asking; Anas Ibn Malik(انس ابن مالك), whose Kuniya(كنيه) is Abu Hamza(أبوحمزه).
He's saying; O Abu Hamza(أبو حمزه) and you have witness that
Anas(انس) said: And where else would I be?
What caught my attention, here is the response that Anas(انس) gave.
He didn't say: Yes, I was there.
He told him: And where else would I be?
And this shows us, a virtue of Anas Ibn Malik رضي الله عنه being the servant of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
He was always with Rasool Allah ﷺ and such an event would not miss him.
He would definitely, be there.
And that's why it's mentioned that Anas Ibn Malik(انس ابن مالك) used to have so many dreams of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
That it goes to the extent that they mentioned that he used to dream about Rasool Allah ﷺ every night.
As he was always with Rasool Allah ﷺ.
An Zohri(عن أظهري), Rasool Allah gave Al-Akrah Bin Habis(اقراء بن حابس) One hundred(100) camels
and he gave Uyeyna Bin Hassan(عيينه بن حصن) One hundred(100) camels.
But he gave Abbas Bin Mardaas(عباس بن مرداس), who was also a chief of the tribe only 50.
So, Al-Abbas(العباس) made some lines of poetry talking about this and saying that
how can my share be less than the share of Al-Akrah Bin Habis(اقرع بن حابس) and Uyeynah(عيينه)
when my father and their fathers were on an equal footing.
And Az-Zuhri(ألظهري) mentions, this narration, he says, that these words reached to Rasool Allah ﷺ.
So Rasool Allah said;
اَنْتَ الْقَائِلْ فاصْبَح نَهْبِيْ وَنَهْبُي الْعَبِيْدِ بَيْنَ الْاَقْرَعْ وَعُيَيْنَهْ
فقالَ: ابو بكر مَا هَكذا قال: يا رسول الله
وَلَكِنْ وَلله مَاكُنْتَ بِشَاعِرٍ وَمَا يَنْبَغِيْ لَكْ فقال: كَيْفَ قَال
فَانْشَدَه’ ابو بكر، فقالَ رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم هُمَا سَوَاءْ مَا يَضُرُّكَ بَأيِّهِمَا بَدَاتْ، َ
ثُمَّ قَالَ رسول الله صلوات الله ولسلام عليه اِقْطَعُوْ عَنِّيْ لِسَانه
Rasool Allah ﷺ told him: Are you the one, who says and then Rasool Ullah mentioned one line of this poem,
that my share and the share of my horse is less than the share of Al-Akrah(اقرع) and Uyeynah(عيينه).
While in the poem Uyeynah(عيينه) is mentioned before Akrah(اقرع).
Rasool Allah mentioned Al-Akrah(اقرع) before Uyeynah(عيينه).
So, Rasool Ullah did not mention the line of poetry correctly.
So, Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) told Rasool Allah ﷺ that is not how he said it
but In the name of Allah, you are not a poet and it's not appropriate for you to be one
and then Rasool Allah ﷺ said: What did he say?
So, Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) mentioned the line as it should be.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ said: They are equal, it doesn't matter which one is mentioned first.
And the reason why I'm bringing up this narration, is to show you that Rasool Allah ﷺ was not a poet
and even when he came to recite that line, he did not follow the meter of the poetry as was known in those times
because Allahعَزّوجَلّ has kept Rasool Allah ﷺ away from poetry,
but Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) mentioned that to Rasool Allah ﷺ and said that
it is not Al-Akrah(الاقرع) before Uyeynah(عيينه) but Uyeynah(عيينه) should be before Akrah(الاقرع).
Anyway the man said: Yes! So, Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Cut away his tongue.
Some people thought that Rasool Allah ﷺ literally meant that, the tongue of Al-Abbas(العباس) should be cut.
When Rasool Allah ﷺ meant that you should give him another 50
and that would cut away his tongue, figuratively speaking,
he will not go around mentioning these words anymore.
And he was given a 100 just like Al-Akrah(الاقرع) and Uyeynah(عيينه).
To show you what Rasool Allah ﷺ them was doing the reason, justification behind it.
In an authentic narration from Safwaan Ibn Umayyah(صفوان إبن أمية), he said;
مَا زالَ رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يُعْطِيْنِيْ مِنْ غَنَائِمِ حُنَيْنِ وَهُوَ اَبْغَضُ خَلْقِ اِلَيَّ
حَتَّى مَا خَلَقَ اللهُ شَيْئا اَحَبَّ اِلَيَّ مِنْهُ
Safwaan(صفوان) says: Rasool Allah ﷺ kept on giving me from the booty of Hunain(حنين)
and he was the worst of the creation to me,
until Allah has not created anything that was more beloved to me than him.
So, it was these gifts that Rasool Allah ﷺ was giving them that soften their hearts
and made them love Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Really brothers and sisters, when you look at the Seerah(سيرة) of Rasool Allah ﷺ, you see
that Rasool Allah ﷺ was a master in dealing with people.
Rasool Allah ﷺ was blessed by Allah with the ability of drawing together the hearts of the community
and forging together an Ummah(امة) and Allahعَزّوجَلّ told him.
لَوْ أَنْفَقْتَ مَا فِي الْأَرْضِ جَمِيعًا مَا أَلَّفْتَ بَيْنَ قُلُوبِهِمْ وَلَٰكِنَّ اللَّهَ أَلَّفَ بَيْنَهُمْ ۚ
If you would spend all of that which is in the world to bring together their hearts you would not do so.
But it is Allah who brought them together.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ has brought these people together.
Rasool Allah ﷺ was the means for bringing them together.
And Allahعَزّوجَلّ is telling Muhammadﷺ, that it is not you but it is from Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
But the point here to make is that Rasool Allah ﷺ we need to understand and learn his Sunnah(سنة).
You know, we sometimes have a limited understanding of what Sunnah(سنة) is.
The way Rasool Allah ﷺ dealt with people, is Sunnah(سنة).
The way he made Da'wah(دعوة) is Sunnah(سنة)
The way Rasool Allah ﷺ fought is Sunnah(سنة), these are all parts of Sunnah(سنة).
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ was giving Safwaan Ibn Umayyah(صفوان إبن أمية), who was an enemy of Rasool Ullah until that moment,
Rasool Allah ﷺ put all of that aside, put it behind him
and was giving Safwaan(صفوان) until, Safwaan(صفوان) was pleased and happy
and he says and admits that, Muhammadﷺ was the most disliked person to me
and now I love him more than anybody else.
Bukhari(إلبخاري) narrates;
حدثنا عمرو بن تغلِب: أَنَّ رسول الله ﷺ أُتِيَّ بِمَالٍ أَوْ سَبِّيٍ فَقَسَّمَه’ فَأعْطَى رِجَالًا، وَتَرَكَ رِجَالًا
فَبَلَغَه’ أَنَّ الَّذِيْنَ تَرَكَهُمْ عَتَبُوْا، فَحَمِدَ الله، وَأَثْنَى عَلَيْهِ، ثُمَّ قَالْ: أَمَّا بَعْدَ:
فَوَالله إِنِّيْ لِأُعْطِي الرَّجُلَ، وَأَدَعُ الرَّجُلْ، وَالَّذِيْ أَدَعُ أَحَبَّ إِلَيَّ مِنَّ الَّذِيْ أُعْطِيْ
وَلَكِنِّي إِنَّمَا أُعْطِيْ أَقْوَاماً لِمَا أَرَى فِيْ قُلُوْبِهِمْ مِنَّ الْجَزَعْ وَالْهَلَعْ،
وَأكِلُ أَقْوَاماً إِلَى مَا جَعَلَ الله فِيْ قُلُوْبِهِمْ مِنَّ الْغِنَى وَالْخَيْر
فيهُمْ عمرو بن تغلب، فَوَالله عمرو يقول
فَوَالله مَا أُحِبُّ أَنَّ لِيْ بِكَلِمَةِ رسول الله ﷺ حُمْرً النَّعْمْ
Amr Bin Taghlib(عمرو بن تغلب) says; That Rasool Allah ﷺ was distributing money or Sabbi(سبي),
Sabbi(سبي) are the women and children.
So, he distributed it, so he gave some men and he left others.
So, Rasool Ullah was told that the ones whom he left were upset that they were left out.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ praised Allah and thanked Him and then said;
In the name of Allah I would give a man and I would leave out another man.
And the one I leave out is more beloved to me than the one I give.
But I am giving people because I see greed in their hearts.
And I entrust others to what Allah has blessed them with contentment and good in their hearts.
And one of them is Amr Bin Taghlib(عمرو بن تغلب).
Amr Bin Taghlib(عمرو بن تغلب) then says; In the name of Allah, I love these words of Rasool Allah ﷺ more than all of the red camels.
And the red camels we mentioned before are the most valuable type of camels.
I mean, if you would give me the entire world of red camels,
I would leave that and rather have Rasool Allah ﷺ give me this badge of honor.
So, you see how Rasool Allah ﷺ has given Safwaan(صفوان)
and that made Safwaan(صفوان) love Rasool Allah ﷺ
and Rasool Ullah prevented Amr Bin Taghlib(عمرو بن تغلب)
and that made Amr Bin Taghlib(عمرو بن تغلب) love Rasool Allah ﷺ more
because Rasool Allah ﷺ mentioned his name and said, that I entrust him to his Eeman(إيمان).
But there were some people, who not only were greedy, but they were complaining
and we will see an example of that and this is mentioned in Bukhari(بخاريْ)
Abu Saeed Al-Khudri(ابوسعيد الخدري) narrates;
قالَ: بَيْنَمَا نَحْنُ عِنْدَ رَسُولِ اللَّهِ صَلَّى اللَّهُ عَلَيْهِ وَسَلَّمَ وَهُوَ يَقْسِمُ قِسْمًا ، أَتَاهُ ذُو الخُوَيْصِرَةِوَهُوَ رَجُلٌ مِنْ بَنِي تَمِيمٍ ،
فَقَالَ : يَا رَسُولَ اللَّهِ اِعْدِلْ ،
فَقَالَ : وَيْلَكَ ، وَمَنْ يَعْدِلُ إِذَا لَمْ أَعْدِلْ
قَدْ خِبْتَ وَخَسِرْتَ إِنْ لَمْ أَكُنْ أَعْدِلُ
فَقَالَ عُمَرُ : يَا رَسُولَ اللَّهِ ، اِئْذَنْ لِي فِيهِ فَأَضْرِبَ عُنُقَهُ ؟
فَقَالَ : دَعْهُ ، فَإِنَّ لَهُ أَصْحَابًا يَحْقِرُ أَحَدُكُمْ صَلاَتَهُ مَعَ صَلاَتِهِمْ ،
وَصِيَامَهُ مَعَ صِيَامِهِمْ ، يَقْرَءُونَ القُرْآنَ لاَ يُجَاوِزُ تَرَاقِيَهُمْ
يَمْرُقُونَ مِنَ الدِّينِ كَمَا يَمْرُقُ السَّهْمُ مِنَ الرَّمِيَّةِ ، يُنْظَرُ إِلَى نَصْلِهِ فَلاَ يُوجَدُ فِيهِ شَيْءٌ
ثُمَّ يُنْظَرُ إِلَى رِصَافِهِ فَمَا يُوجَدُ فِيهِ شَيْءٌ ، ثُمَّ يُنْظَرُ إِلَى نَضِيِّهِ ، - وَهُوَ قِدْحُهُ - ، فَلاَ يُوجَدُ فِيهِ شَيْءٌ
ثُمَّ يُنْظَرُ إِلَى قُذَذِهِ فَلاَ يُوجَدُ فِيهِ شَيْءٌ ،
قَدْ سَبَقَ الفَرْثَ وَالدَّمَ ، آيَتُهُمْ رَجُلٌ أَسْوَدُ ، إِحْدَى عَضُدَيْهِ مِثْلُ ثَدْيِ المَرْأَةِ
أَوْ مِثْلُ البَضْعَةِ تَدَرْدَرُ ، وَيَخْرُجُونَ عَلَى حِينِ فُرْقَةٍ مِنَ النَّاسِ
قَالَ أَبُو سَعِيدٍ : فَأَشْهَدُ أَنِّي سَمِعْتُ هَذَا الحَدِيثَ مِنْ رَسُولِ اللَّهِ صَلَّى اللَّهُ عَلَيْهِ وَسَلَّمَ
وَأَشْهَدُ أَنَّ عَلِيَّ بْنَ أَبِي طَالِبٍ قَاتَلَهُمْ وَأَنَا مَعَهُ
فَأَمَرَ بِذَلِكَ الرَّجُلِ فَالْتُمِسَ فَأُتِيَ بِهِ ، حَتَّى نَظَرْتُ إِلَيْهِ عَلَى نَعْتِ النَّبِيِّ صَلَّى اللَّهُ عَلَيْهِ وَسَلَّمَ الَّذِي نَعَتَهُ
Abu Saeed Al-Khudri(ابو سعيد الخدري) says; We were with Rasool Allah ﷺ while he was distributing a booty
and he was approached by Zul Khuwaisrah(ذو الخويسره) and he is a man from Bannu Tamim(بنو تميم).
So, he said: O Rasool Ullah, be just.
Subhaan Allah(سبحان الله), I mean, this man is speaking to Rasool Allah ﷺ
the messenger from Allah, and he's telling him: Be just.
This man, who was until, quite a short while ago, a disbeliever making Sujood(سجود) to an idol
is telling the best of creation, Be just.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Woe to you and who would be just if I am not just.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه said: O Rasool Ullah allow me, to cut off his neck.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said leave him because he will have companions
you will belittle your Salah(صلاة) to their Salah(صلاة)
and you would belittle your fasting, compared to their fasting
they would recite Qur'an but it would not leave their throats.
It would not go beyond their throats
they would leave the religion, just like an arrow would leave its target.
So, you would look at the blade, and there's no blood on it.
And then you would look at the binding, and you would not find nothing on it.
And you would look at the rest of the arrow,
and you would find the shaft and you would find nothing on it.
An explanation of what this is.?
If an archer is strong and he shoots the arrow with such force,
the arrow could hit the game and could pass to it so fast
that the archer cannot even recognize, that the target was hit.
And then he goes to pick up the arrow, to see if there's any traces of blood on it.
And he would find nothing, he would look at the blade, there's nothing
he would look at the binding that brings the blade to the shaft, he would find nothing
then he would look at the shaft itself and he would find nothing.
This is an analogy that Rasool Allah ﷺ gave of how fast these people would leave religion.
I mean, they are so extreme that they would leave the religion so swiftly, you couldn't even recognize that.
And this is a very interesting analogy that Rasool Allah ﷺ gave about these people.
Because they pray and Rasool Allah ﷺ is saying that they're praying more than the Sahabah(صحابه)
and they are fasting and they're fasting more
and they recite Qur'an, but it doesn't leave their throats.
Why? Because they're not following the meanings.
It's just voice coming out from the throat but there's no implication of it.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ said, and their sign is a dark man
and one of his arms I mean, he doesn't have a full arm he just has a trunk of an arm
and it looks like a breast of a woman.
So, Abu Saeed Al-Khudri(ابوسعيد الخدري) said: I testified that I heard these words from Rasool Allah ﷺ
and I testify that Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) is the one, who fought them
and I was with him and he ordered that you search for that man and we found him
and we saw that the description of Rasool Allah ﷺ, this man fitted exactly.
Let's see some words from Ibn Hajar(إبن حجر), in his commentary on this Hadith(حديث);
قَالَ اِبْنِ هُبَيْرَهْ
Ibn Hajar(إبن حجر) says, that Ibn Hubairah(ابن هبيره) said;
وَفِي الْحَدِيثِ أَنَّ قِتَالَ الْخَوَارِجِ أَوْلَى مِنْ قِتَالِ الْمُشْرِكِينَ
وَالْحِكْمَةُ فِيهِ أَنَّ فِي قِتَالِهِمْ حِفْظَ رَأْسِ مَالِ الْإِسْلَامِ
وَفِي قِتَالِ أَهْلِ الشِّرْكِ طَلَبُ الرِّبْحِ، وَحِفْظُ رَأْسِ الْمَالِ أَوْلَى
In this Hadith(حديث), we learn that fighting the Khawarij(خوارج) is a priority over fighting the disbelievers.
And the wisdom behind that, is because fighting the KhawariJ(خوارج) is a protection of the capital,
while fighting the disbelievers is seeking profit
and protecting the capital takes precedence, over making a profit.
And this is a rule that applies to fighting all of the Murtaddeen(مرتدين).
Because they are eating the Ummah(امة) from within.
While when you fight the disbelievers
you're fighting them to bring them obviously here, they're talking about fighting the disbelievers in terms of Da'wah(دعوة).
So, protecting the capital takes precedence over making profit.
And then he says;
وَفِيْهِ الْتَحْذِيْرمِنَّ الْغُلُوِّفِيْ الدِّيَانَه وَالتَنَطَّعْ فِي الْعِبَادَهْ بِالْحَمْلِ عَلَى النَفْسِ فِيْمَا لَمْ يَاْذَنْ فِيْهِ الشَّرْعَ
And he said: There's a warning in this Hadith(حديث) from going to extremes, in religion
and going to extremes in worship in ways that Islam has not allowed, Shariyah(شريعة) has not allowed.
And then he says;
وَاِنَّمَا نَدَبَ اِلَى شِّدَةِ عَلَى الْكُفَّارِ وَاِلَى رَاْفَةِ بِالْمُؤمِنِيْنَ فَعَكَسَ ذَالِكَ الْخَوَارِجْ كَمَا تَقَدَّمَ بَيَانَهْ
Our religion has encouraged us to be rough with the Kuffar(كفار) and soft with the believers.
And the Khawarij(الخوارج) did the opposite of that, like we have seen
because Rasool Allah ﷺ gives us a very important sign of the signs of Al-Khawarij(الخوارج)
and it's very important to keep in mind whenever we want to know who the Khawarij(خوارج) are?
And that sign is;
يَقْتُلُوْنَ اَهْلَ الْاِسْلَامِ وَيَتْرَكُوْنَ اَهْلَ الْاَوْسَانْ
They kill the Muslims and they leave the disbelievers.
This is an important sign of the signs of the Khawarij(خوارج).
An example of that Abdallah Bin Khabbab(عبدالله بن خباب), he is the son of the companion Khabbab Ibn Arat(خباب ابن ارت),
he was traveling along with his wife and he was stopped by the Khawarij(خوارج).
They said: Who are you.? He said: I am the son of Khabbab Ibn Arat(خباب ابن ارت).
Everybody knows who he is, a companion of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
And they killed him
and they opened up the stomach of his wife
and killed her and drew out the fetus, she was pregnant.
And then, they took some belongings that were owned by Christian or a Jew.
And then some of them said: No, you have to return it, because these are Ahluz-Zimmah(أهل ضمه).
So, you can see an example here.
They are following Warra'a(ورع) and Taqwa(تقوى) when it comes to Ahluz-Zimmah(أهل ضمه)
but when it comes to the Muslims, they killed the son of a companion of Rasool Allah صلوات الله وسلام عليه.
This is one of the most important qualities of Khawarij(خوارج)
is their animosity, hatred, roughness toward Muslims.
And then when it comes to the Kuffar(كفار), they turned a blind eye towards them.
وَفِيْهِ جَوَازُ
And by the way, that incident that I mentioned was, started the war between Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) and Khawarij(خوارج).
Because Ali(على) said: Leave them alone until, they kill or they rob, then we will fight them.
So, when they killed Abdallah Bin Khabbab(عبدالله بن خباب) and they took his belongings
that is when Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) ordered that, they should be fought.
And then he says;
وَفِيْهِ جَوَازُ قِتَالِ مَنْ خَرَجَ عَنْ طَاعَةِ الْاِمَامُ الْعَادِلْ ، وَمَنْ نَصَبَ الْحَرْبَ فَقَاتَلَ عَلَى اَعْتَقَادٍ فَاسِدْ
He says; There is evidence here for fighting, the ones who revolt against the just Imam(إمام), the just leader
and the ones, who are fighting for a false belief.
So, there is an evidence here for fighting the ones, who are fighting for a false belief,
and fighting the ones, who revolt against a just leader
such as Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب), the ones who revolt against him.
وَمَنْ خَرَجَ يَقْطَعَ الطُّرُقْ وَيُخِيْفِ السَّبِيْلَ وَيَسْعَى فِيْ الْاَرْضِ بِالْفَسَادْ
And the ones, who spread corruption on earth and commit armed robbery
there is an evidence here that they should be fought.
And keep note of what Ibn Hajar(ابن حجر) is saying next.
وَاَمَّا مَنْ خَرَجَ عَنْ طَاعَةِ اِمَامٍ جَاِئٍر اَرَادَ الْغَلَبَةَ عَلَى مَالِهِ اَوْ نَفْسِهِ اَوْ اَهْلِهِ فَهُوَ مَعْذُوْرٌ وَلَايَحِلُّ قِتَالُهْ
He says; But the ones revolt against an oppressive leader.
And notice here, he is not saying that disbelieving leader, he is saying an oppressive leader.
Who wants to take over his wealth, or to kill him, or to abuse his family, then he is excused.
And it is not allowed to fight him.
So, the ones who revolt against the unjust leaders.
Ibn Hajar(ابن حجر) is saying that it is Haram(حرام) to fight them
and they are excused for fighting.
And he says that if the police force or the army of an unjust ruler comes to take away your wealth or to kill you
or to abuse your family then you can fight back.
He says;
وَلَايَحِلُّ قِتَالُهْ وَلَه’ اَنْ يَدْفَعَ عَنْ نَفْسِهِ وَمَالِهِ وَاَهْلِهِ بِقَدَرْ طَاقَتِهْ
And you can defend yourself and your wealth and your family according to your ability.
So, and this is talking about the unjust leader.
But if the leader is a disbeliever then it is the consensus of the Ulemaa(علماء) that it is Wajib(واجب),
it is obligatory to fight him, you cannot submit to a disbelieving leader.
وَسَيَاتِيْ بِيَانُ ذَالِكَ فِيْ كِتَابِ الْفِتَنْ
He said: And we will explain that in the book of Fittan(فتن).
And then he says;
وَقَدْ اَخْرَجَ الطَّبَرِيْ بِسَنَدٍ صَحِيْح عَنْ عبد الله بن حارث
عَنْ رَجُلٍ مِنْ بَنِيْ نَضَرْ عَنْ عَلِي وَذَكَرَ الْخَوَارج فَقَال
اِنْ خَالَفُوْا اِمَامًا عَدْلًا فَقَاتِلُوْهُمْ، وَاِنْ خَالَفُوْا اِمَامًا جَاِئرًا فَلَا تُقَاتِلُوْهُمْ فَاِنَّ لَهُمْ مَقَالًا
At-Tabari(الطبري) narrates with an authentic chain from Abdullah Bin Harith(عَبد الله بن حارث),
from a man from Banni Nazar(بني نضر) from Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب)
that he said about Al-Khawarij(الخوارج),
if they go against a just ruler then they should be fought.
But if they go against an unjust ruler, then do not fight them because they have an evidence.
قُلْت :وَعَلَى ذَالِكْ يُحْمَلْ مَا وَقَعَ لاْحُسَيْن بِن عَلي ثٌمَّ لِاَهْلِ الْمَدِيْنَه فِيْ الْحَرَّةْ
ثُمَّ لِعَبْدِالله بِن زُبَيْر ثُمَّ لِلْقُرَّاءِ الَّذِيْنَ خَرَجُوْاعَلَى الْحُجَاجْ فِيْ قِصَّةِ عبد الرحمن بن محمدبن اَلْاَشْعَثْ وَالله اَعْلَمْ
And then he says, and that is what we should consider, happend with Al-Hussain Bin Ali(ألحسين بن علي)
and people of Madina when they revolted.
And Abdallah Bin Zubair(عبد الله بن زبير) and then the scholars who revolted against Al-Hujjaj(ألحجاج)
in the story of Abdur Rahman Bin Muhammad Al-Ash'ath(عبد الرحمن بن محمدالاشعث) and Allah knows best.
So, Ibn Hajar(ابن حجر) here is mentioning examples of those who revolted against unjust leaders
and he mentioned Abdullah Bin Zubair(عبد الله بن زبير) and Hussain Ibn Ali(حسين بن علي) and the people of Madina
and Abdur Rahman Ibn Ash'as(عبد الرحمن بن اشعث) as an examples.
The people of Hawazin(هوازن), they sent a delegation to Rasool Ullah صلوات الله وسلام عليه
asking Rasool Ullah to give them back their property because they lost everything.
Their women and their children and their live stock was all gone.
I mean, imagine an entire tribe, only the men are left and everything else is taken away from them.
And this narration is in Al-Bukhari(بخاريْ)
أَنَّ رَسُولَ اللَّهِ صَلَّى اللَّهُ عَلَيْهِ وَسَلَّمَ ، قَام حِينَ جَاءَهُ وَفْدُ هَوَازِنَ مُسْلِمِينَ
فَسَأَلُوهُ أَنْ يَرُدَّ إِلَيْهِمْ أَمْوَالَهُمْ وَسَبْيَهُمْ
فَقَالَ لَهُمْ رَسُولُ اللَّهِ صَلَّى اللَّهُ عَلَيْهِ وَسَلَّمَ : أَحَبُّ الحَدِيثِ إِلَيَّ أَصْدَقُهُ ،
فَاخْتَارُوا إِحْدَى الطَّائِفَتَيْنِ ، إِمَّا السَّبْيَ وَإِمَّا المَالَ
وَقَدْ كُنْتُ اسْتَأْنَيْتُ بِهِمْ ، وَقَدْ كَانَ رَسُولُ اللَّهِ صَلَّى اللَّهُ عَلَيْهِ وَسَلَّمَ انْتَظَرَ آخِرَهُمْ بِضْعَ عَشْرَةَ لَيْلَةً حِينَ قَفَلَ مِنَ الطَّائِفِ
When Hawazin(هوازن) came to accept Islam
they asked Rasool Allah ﷺ to return to them their wealth and their women and children.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ said: The most beloved words to me are the most truthful.
So, choose one of two, either your women and children or the wealth.
Rasool Allah ﷺ told them, I cannot give both back.
I will give you either the women and children or the wealth.
And I waited for you, so Rasool Allah ﷺ is telling them,
I actually waited before distributing the Ghaneemah(غنيمه).
With the hope that you would come to me, so I could give it back to you.
But now it's already divided.
I mean, it's already now within the property of Muslim individuals.
So, I cannot take it away from them and give it back to you.
But he told them choose one of the two.
So, they said;
If you are giving us the choice, then obviously, we're going to choose our woman and children.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ told them;
I am going to give them back to you but I have to appeal to the Muslims.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ stood up in front of the Muslims. Praised Allahعَزّوجَلّ. And then said;
أَمَّا بَعْدُ ، فَإِنَّ إِخْوَانَكُمْ هَؤُلاَءِ قَدْ جَاءُونَا تَائِبِينَ
وَإِنِّي قَدْ رَأَيْتُ أَنْ أَرُدَّ إِلَيْهِمْ سَبْيَهُمْ مَنْ أَحَبَّ منكم أَنْ يُطَيِّبَ ،بذالك فَلْيَفْعَلْ
وَمَنْ أَحَبَّ مِنْكُمْ أَنْ يَكُونَ عَلَى حَظِّهِ حَتَّى نُعْطِيَهُ إِيَّاهُ مِنْ أَوَّلِ مَا يُفِيءُ اللَّهُ عَلَيْنَا فَلْيَفْعَلْ
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Your brothers have come repenting, they became Muslim.
And I want to give back to them their women and children.
So, whoever among you, would allow to give them back what belongs to them, then he should do so.
And whoever wants to be compensated,
then I will compensate them from the first Ghaneemah(غنيمه) that we get.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ is telling them, if you want to give them back what belongs to them
then that is better do it.
If you want to give it back with a promise of reimbursement for what you have given
that I will do that from the first Ghaneemah(غنيمه) that I get after this battle.
So, the Muhajireen(مهاجرين) and Al-Ansaar(أنْصَار) in the narration of Al-Bukhari(بخاريْ), it says that they all gave it back
but Ibn Is'haaq(إبن إسحاق) mentions, the scholars of Seerah(سيرة) say that the Muhajireen(مهاجرين) said;
We would give up what we have, the Ansaar(أنْصَار) said the same,
but then Al-Akrah Bin Habis(الاقرع بن حابس) stood and said: Me and my tribe will not give up, what we have.
Oyeynah Bin Hassan(عيينه بن حصن) said: We will not give up what we have.
And then Al-Abbas Bin Mardaas(العباس بن مرداس) said: We will not give up what we have.
But then his tribe Bannu Sulaim(بَنُوسُلَيم) stood up and said: No! We are going to give up, what we have.
So, Al-Abbas(العباس) told them,
وَهَنْتُمُوْنِيْ
You have disgraced me.
But they have done the right thing.
Rasool Allah ﷺ appealed to the people to give it back.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ said: I will not know, who has given back and who has not.
So, let Urafa'a(عرفاء), Urfaa(عرفاء) are the Shuyookh(شيوخ) of the tribes, the leaders of the tribes.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Let them report to me.
Who has given up what they have and who didn't.
Anyway, the women and children were returned to Hawazin(هوازن).
While the live stock was split, it says that every individual got 40 sheep.
It tells you that there was a huge Ghaneemah(غنيمه).
Malik Ibn Auf(مالك بن عوف) received a message from Rasool Allah ﷺ
saying that if you become Muslim, I will give you, what belongs to you
and on top of that, I will give you 100 camels.
So, Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله) Malik Bin Auf(مالك بن عوف) sneaked out from At-Taef(ألطائف)
and he was there when it was besieged and he carried on resisting, until that moment.
So, now when he is told by Rasool Allah ﷺ that I will give you, your property back, he came and he accepted Islam,
and then he lead an army from his people, who became Muslim, against the people of At-Taef(ألطائف).
I mean, he is the one who started the war against Rasool Ullah.
And now he became Muslim and he is fighting against the ones, whom he encouraged to fight Rasool Allah ﷺ in the first place.
So, again it shows us how Rasool Allah ﷺ was winning the hearts of the people.
Ka'ab Ibn Zuhair(كعب ابن زهير) also became Muslim.
Ka'ab Ibn Zuhair(كعب ابن زهير) was one of the poets, who used to use their poetry against Rasool Ullah صلوات الله وسلام عليه.
His brother sent him a message telling him that Rasool Allah ﷺ is executing the poets who spoke against him.
So, you either come to him as Muslim or flee before you're killed.
So, Ka'ab(كعب) was very worried about this.
And he was concerned that he might be killed.
And the people who were advising him, were causing him this fear.
But anyway, he decided that he will give it a try and go back to Rasool Allah ﷺ.
So, he went to Rasool Ullah
and Rasool Allah ﷺ did not know him.
So, he went to Rasool Allah and said: Ka'ab Ibn Zuhair(كعب ابن زهير) came to you repenting,
and he wants to become Muslim, do you accept his Islam, Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Yes! Let him come.
He said: I am Ka'ab Ibn Zuhair(كعب ابن زهير).
Then he gave his Bay'ah(بيعة) to Rasool Allah ﷺ.
And he stood up and gave a wonderful poem, praising Rasool Allah صلوات الله وسلام عليه.
And the story goes, that Rasool Allah ﷺ told the Sahabah(صحابه) to listen to this poem.
And then Rasool Allah, gave him his cloak, Al-Burda(البرده)
And it is this Burda(برده) according to the stories,
that ended up in the hands of the Khulafa(خلافاء) of Bannu Abbas(بنوعباس).
They considered it to be Baraka(بركة), because it's belongs to Rasool Allah ﷺ,
and it would be handed down from one Khaleefah(خليفه) to the next.
Also Rasool Allah ﷺ we are talking about the events that happened within that year.
Rasool Allah ﷺ sent men from the tribe of Ahmas(أحمس) to Zul Khalsa(ذوالخلصه) to destroy it and they destroyed it.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ, was destroying all of the remnants of Jahiliyyah(جَاهلِيَّة)
all of these false idols, Asnaam(إصنام) were being destroyed.
And this was bringing an end to the false worship in the land of Hijaaz(حجاز) and the rest of the Arabian Peninsula.
This is the end of the events of the eighth year of Hijrah(هحرة)
In sha Allah Ta'ala(اِن شاء اهِي تعالى), we will move on to the next in our following session.
صَلَّى الله عَلى سَيَّدِنَا محمد وَعَلى اَلِهِ وَ صَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًاكَثِيْرَا
وَالسلا م عليكم ورحمة الله  وبركاته